Duane Spencer Hatch Collection 1912-1982, (bulk 1940-1982)
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Duane Spencer Hatch Collection 1912-1982, (bulk 1940-1982)
MS 482
Hatch, D. Spencer (Duane Spencer); Hatch, Emily Gilchriest, 1897-
Duane Spencer Hatch (1888-1963) was an agriculturalist, researcher, and pioneer in rural reconstruction and community development. This collection contains materials pertaining to the life and work of Duane Spencer Hatch. Hatch conducted research in Costa Rica, India, Sri Lanka (formally known as Ceylon), Mexico, and in Parker, Arizona. The collection contains research materials such as field notes, diaries, correspondence, and reports, along with photographic materials concerning these rural locations. Personal materials in the collection from Hatch, and his wife Emily Hatch, include bibliographic and biographic materials, correspondence, publicly files, and photographs. Audio and visual materials in the collection include movies created by Hatch in movie reel and DVD format and talks given by Hatch in record and CD format.
9 Linear Feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None
Biographical Note
Duane Spencer Hatch (1888-1963) was born on a farm in Greenwich, New York and was a pioneer in rural reconstruction and community development. He graduated from Cornell University in 1915 with a B.Sc in Agriculture, an M.Sc in Agriculture in 1916, and another Master’s degree in Rural Sociology, Economics, and Education. He continued his education at Yale University and Cornell University for a PhD in Rural Sociology, Economics, and Education, which he received in 1928. In 1916, Hatch went to India and Mesopotamia for service with British and Indian troops during World War I, under the auspices of the Indian National Council, Young Men’s Christian Association (YMCA). He later returned to India, with his wife Emily Hatch, to begin his long career in rural reconstruction under the support of the YMCAs of India and was later appointed to the United Nations' Food and Agricultural Committee. Starting in the 1940s, he directed community developments in Mexico. After retiring from the YMCA, he served as the director of an agricultural project for the Pan American Union in Costa Rica. Hatch then went on to establish a Community Development Center for the United Nations (UNESCO) in Sri Lanka (formally known as Ceylon). From 1957-1960, he worked in Parker, Arizona as the Director of Community Development for the Colorado River Tribes Reservation. He then retired to Tucson, Arizona where he became a consultant to the Sociology Department at the University of Arizona and Director of Field Work for students working towards their MA Degree in Community Development.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into 5 series.
Series I: Personal 1912-1982, undated
Subseries 1: Duane Spencer Hatch
Subseries 2: Emily Gilchriest Hatch
Series II: Research Materials 1915-1982, undated
Subseries 1: Assorted Research Materials
Subseries 2: Geographic Locations
Subseries 3: Organizations
Series III: Written Works 1940-1956, undated
Subseries 1: Reports, Programmes, and Memorandums
Subseries 2: Typescripts and Publications
Series IV: Photographs and Albums 1916-1965, undated
Subseries 1: Assorted Photographs
Subseries 2: Geographic Locations and Villages
Subseries 3: Personal
Subseries 4: Publicity Photographs
Subseries 5: Photo Albums
Series V: Oversized Materials 1947-1963, undated
Subseries 1: Audio and Publicity Materials
Subseries 2: Movie Reels
Scope and Content Note
The inclusive dates for this collection are 1912-1982, with the bulk of the material dating from 1940-1970. The materials in the collection relate to Duane Spencer Hatch, his personal life and his research. Personal correspondence, publicity materials from his popular works,Up From Poverty and Toward Freedom From Want, and materials from a possible book about the life and work of Hatch is found in this collection. His wife, Emily Hatch, accompanied Hatch to rural locations to aid in his research and to do some research on her own. Personal materials from her include business correspondence, speeches conducted, and written reports and typescripts. Hatch’s research materials about rural reconstruction, community development, and fundamental education from Arizona, India, Sri Lanka (formally known as Ceylon), Costa Rica, and Mexico are contained in this collection. When identifying the folders in the collection, Ceylon and Sri Lanka are interchangeable. Note that Hatch’s research materials use the term Ceylon, because he conducted his research before the change of name to Sri Lanka. Research materials include personal diaries and notebooks, reports, correspondence, and hand written notes. Hatch worked with multiple organizations including UNESCO, YMCAs of India, the Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations, and the International Alliance of Women. Materials pertaining to these organizations include reports, correspondence, and publicity materials. The collection also contains photographs, personal photo albums, prints, positives, and negatives of the Hatch family and the locations and villages that they researched and visited. The collection contains movie reels and access copies in DVD format of movies made by Duane Spencer Hatch and one particular movie,The Mexico Story, was a collaboration with his brother, Ira Hatch. Audio materials include records and access copies in CD format of talks given by Duane Spencer Hatch about the work he has done in India, Mexico, and Costa Rica.
Access Terms
Hatch, D. Spencer (Duane Spencer)
Hatch, Emily Gilchriest, 1897-
Rural development--Research
Colorado River Indian Tribes of the Colorado River Indian Reservation, Arizona and California--Rural conditions
Costa Rica--Rural conditions
India--Rural conditions
Mexico--Rural conditions
Sri Lanka--Rural conditions
Unesco--Education and rural development
Unesco--India
Young Men's Christian Association (India)
Container List
- Series I: Personal, 1912-1982; undated
  This series is arranged alphabetically and by subject. It contains materials from the personal lives of Duane Spencer Hatch and his wife, Emily Gilchriest Hatch. Contents include biographical materials, correspondence, publicity materials, and materials for a possible book based on the life and work of Duane Spencer Hatch.
  - Subseries 1: Duane Spencer Hatch
    - Accomplishment Bulletins, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Bibliographies, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Biographical Materials, 1912-1961 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Book on Hatch–Introduction, 1974-1982 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Book on Hatch–Chapter One India, 1940-1982 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Book on Hatch–Chapter Two Mexico, 1944-1982 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Book on Hatch–Chapter Three Costa Rica, 1947-1982 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Book on Hatch–Chapter Four UNESCO India, 1950-1982 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Book on Hatch–Chapter Five UNESCO Ceylon, 1955-1982 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Book on Hatch–Chapter Six Colorado River Tribe, 1956-1982 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence Business, 1917-1949 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence Business, 1950-1974; undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Newspaper Clippings, 1934-1957; undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Obituaries and Memorial Tributes, 1963-1964 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Publicity Files–Further Upwards, 1935-1939; undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Publicity Files–Toward Freedom From Want, 1949-1970; undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Publicity Files–Up From Poverty, 1939-1963; undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Publicity Files–Up From Poverty Movie Notes, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Receipts, 1958-1961 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Subseries 2: Emily Gilchriest Hatch
    - Biographical Materials, 1953-1969; undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Correspondence Business, 1936-1978 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Correspondence Condolences 1, 1963-1964; undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Correspondence Condolences 2, 1963-1964; undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Newspaper Clippings, 1927-1932; undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Speeches, 1963-1964 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Series II: Research Materials, 1915-1982; undated
  This series is arranged topically. It contains research materials used by and created by Duane Spencer Hatch. These materials would include field notes, reports, correspondence, newspaper clippings and materials for various projects he was involved in.
  - Subseries 1: Assorted Research Materials
    - Community Development, 1963-1981; undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Field Diaries and Notebooks, 1915-1937 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Field Diaries and Notebooks, 1939-1941 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Field Diaries and Notebooks, 1942-1954 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Field Diaries and Notebooks, 1955-1959 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Field Diaries and Notebooks, 1960-1964 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Field Diaries and Notebooks, undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Field Notes, 1939-1963; undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Newsletters and Bulletins, 1962-1975; undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Newspaper Clippings, 1974-1976; undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Subseries 2:Geographic Locations
    - Arizona-Colorado River Tribe–Correspondence and Bulletins, 1958-1977; undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Arizona-Colorado River Tribe–Research and Reports, 1961-1977; undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Arizona-Mojave Tribe–Research and Reports, 1959-1972; undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Costa Rica–Research and Reports, 1964-1965; undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - India–Addresses by Duane Spencer Hatch, 1915-1941; undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - India–Booklets and Pamphlets, 1931-1972 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - India–Correspondence, 1918-1974; undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - India–Field Notes, 1961-1974; undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - India–Newspaper Clippings, 1916-1939 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - India–Newspaper Clippings, 1940-1976; undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - India–Research and Reports, 1918-1959; undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - India-Martandam–Correspondence, 1933-1973; undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - India-Martandam–Reports, 1938-1974 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - India-Martandam–Research, 1916-1966; undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Mexico–Research and Reports, 1942-1963; undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Pakistan–Social Welfare Training Project Research, 1953-1982; undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Sri Lanka–Ceylon Project Evaluation Materials by Burroughs, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Sri Lanka– Ceylon Project Evaluation Materials by Wahlund, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Sri Lanka–Ceylon Project Evaluation Materials Evaluation Handbooks, 1955-1963; undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Sri Lanka–Ceylon Project Evaluation Materials Notes, 1952-1964; undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Sri Lanka–Ceylon Project Evaluation Materials Outlines and Reports, 1964; undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Sri Lanka– Research and Reports, 1927-1974; undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Sri Lanka–Village Surveys, 1953-1955 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Subseries 3: Organizations
    - International Alliance of Women–Correspondence, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - International Alliance of Women–Golden Jubilee Congress Conference Materials, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - International Alliance of Women–Newspaper Clippings, 1955; undated (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Young Men’s Christian Association of India–Correspondence to the Hatches, 1917-1973; undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Young Men’s Christian Association of India–Newsletters to Members, 1933-1971; undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Young Men’s Christian Association of India–Newspaper Clippings, 1965; undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Young Men’s Christian Association of India–Publicity Materials, 1926-1975; undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Young Men’s Christian Association of India–Research and Reports, 1969-1970; undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Series III: Written Works, 1940-1956; undated
  This series is arranged alphabetically. It is comprised of reports, programmes, and memorandums written by Duane Spencer Hatch, from conferences that he attended, or from committees he served on. Typescripts and publications from Duane Spencer Hatch and his wife, Emily Hatch, are represented as well. The typescript What Did He Leave To Grow? by Emily Hatch is lacking chapter eight.
  - Subseries 1: Reports, Programmes, and Memorandums
    - Arab States Fundamental Education Centre Egypt-Training Programme, December 1952-October 1954 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Arab States Fundamental Education Centre Egypt-Training Programme, September 8-December 19, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Arab States Fundamental Education Centre Egypt-Training Programme, February 2-June 26, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Final Report of the Specialist for Training Rural Workers, June 1952-May 1953 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Final Report of the Specialist for Training Rural Workers With Note From Emily Hatch, June 1952-May 1953 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Final Report on the Rural Welfare Programme of the UNTAA-Government of Pakistan Social Welfare Project, February-December, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Report of the First Session of the Conference of the Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations, October 16-November 1, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Report of the UNESCO Adviser to Government of India on Rural Adult Education, March 1-September 1, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - The Government of Ceylon UNESCO Fundamental Education Project-Minneriya Area an Analysis of the First Four Years, 1951-1955 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - UNESCO Government of Ceylon Fundamental Education Project Report, March 1- September 1, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - UNESCO Memorandum of Higher Education in Relation to Rural India, April 1949 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - UNESCO Report on a Conference on Techniques of Evaluation, May 30-June 1, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - UNESCO Training for International Service in Fundamental Education Group Training Scheme India, December 1953-July 1954 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Subseries 2: Typescripts and Publications
    - Beyond the Ends of the Roads by Duane Spencer Hatch, undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Rural Reconstruction and Evangelism by Duane Spencer Hatch, 1940 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Too Big To Measure by Duane Spencer Hatch, undated (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - What Are We Up To At Minneriya? by Duane Spencer Hatch, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - What Did He Leave To Grow? by Emily Hatch, undated (Box 3, Folder 23)
- Series IV: Photographs and Albums, 1916-1965; undated
  This series is arranged topically and alphabetically. It contains photographs and negatives of Duane Spencer Hatch, his wife Emily, and their family in their personal lives and in the countries they traveled for research. Photographs also include Hatch’s research destinations, the groups of peoples in those countries, organizations he belonged to, and the work he did in rural reconstruction and education. Photo albums created by the Hatches are in this series as well. One oversized photo can be found in Box 8. Subseries 4: Publicity Photos is lacking Book Into Their New Day-Group 2.
  - Subseries 1: Assorted Photographs
    - Agriculture, 1953-1958; undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Boats, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Dancing, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Dwellings, 1958; undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Identified People, 1918-1963; undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Landscapes, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Military, undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Street Scenes, undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Textiles, undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Unidentified Children, undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Unidentified Groups, 1953-1965; undated (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Unidentified People, undated (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Unidentified People with Animals, undated (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Yale group in India, 1922 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Young Men’s Christian Association, 1917; undated (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Subseries 2: Geographic Locations and Villages
    - Arizona-Parker, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Costa Rica, undated (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - India-Assorted Photographs, 1930-1933; undated (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - India-Martandam, 1920-1956; undated (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - India-Travancore, 1930; undated (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - India-UNESCO, undated (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - India-Vilathavillai, undated (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - India-Young Men’s Christian Association, undated (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Mexico-Assorted Photographs, undated (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - Mexico-Jacatepec, 1958-1962; undated (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - Mexico- Tepetlapa, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - Sri Lanka-Assorted Photographs, undated (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - Sri Lanka-Diulakana, 1954 (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - Sri Lanka-Ginidamana, 1954; undated (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - Sri Lanka-Giritale, undated (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - Sri Lanka-Gurugodella, 1954; undated (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Sri Lanka-Gutwewa, 1955; undated (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Sri Lanka-Hingierakamana, undated (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - Sri Lanka-Hinguraka, undated (Box 4, Folder 34)
    - Sri Lanka-Hingurakgoda, 1953-1955; undated (Box 4, Folder 35)
    - Sri Lanka-Horiwila, 1953; undated (Box 4, Folder 36)
    - Sri Lanka-Hukwewa, undated (Box 4, Folder 37)
    - Sri Lanka-Jaffna, undated (Box 4, Folder 38)
    - Sri Lanka-Kadulla, undated (Box 4, Folder 39)
    - Sri Lanka-Kalahagala, 1955; undated (Box 4, Folder 40)
    - Sri Lanka-Kantalai, 1955; undated (Box 4, Folder 41)
    - Sri Lanka-Madivigiri, undated (Box 4, Folder 42)
    - Sri Lanka-Manampitiya, 1955; undated (Box 4, Folder 43)
    - Sri Lanka-Polonnaruwa, undated (Box 4, Folder 44)
    - Sri Lanka-Puduweli, 1955; undated (Box 4, Folder 45)
    - Sri Lanka-Tamil, undated (Box 4, Folder 46)
    - Sri Lanka-Timbirigaswewa, undated (Box 4, Folder 47)
    - Sri Lanka-Trincomalee, 1955; undated (Box 4, Folder 48)
    - Sri Lanka-UNESCO Fundamental Education Project, 1954; undated (Box 4, Folder 49)
    - Sri Lanka-Yakuri, undated (Box 4, Folder 50)
    - Sri Lanka-Yoda Ela, 1955; undated (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - Subseries 3: Personal
    - Duane Spencer Hatch Candid Photographs, 1918-1957; undated (Box 4, Folder 52)
    - Duane Spencer Hatch Headshots, undated (Box 4, Folder 53)
    - Duane Spencer Hatch in Garden, undated (Box 4, Folder 54)
    - Duane Spencer Hatch with Groups, undated (Box 4, Folder 55)
    - Duane Spencer Hatch and Emily Hatch, undated (Box 4, Folder 56)
    - Duane Spencer Hatch and Emily Hatch with Groups, undated (Box 4, Folder 57)
    - Emily Hatch, undated (Box 4, Folder 58)
    - Emily Hatch with Groups, undated (Box 4, Folder 59)
    - Hatch Family, undated (Box 4, Folder 60)
    - School House Built by Hatches in Greenwich NY, undated (Box 4, Folder 61)
  - Subseries 4: Publicity Photographs
    - Book Into Their New Day–Group 1, 1963; undated (Box 4, Folder 62)
    - Book Into Their New Day–Group 3-Ceylon, 1950; undated (Box 4, Folder 63)
    - Book Into Their New Day–Group 4-Mexico, undated (Box 4, Folder 64)
    - Book Into Their New Day–Group 5-Ceylon, undated (Box 4, Folder 65)
    - Book on Ceylon, 1953-1955; undated (Box 4, Folder 66)
    - Book on Hatch–Assorted, 1916-1927; undated (Box 4, Folder 67)
    - Book on Hatch–Chapter One India, undated (Box 4, Folder 68)
    - Book on Hatch–Chapter Two Mexico, 1958; undated (Box 4, Folder 69)
    - Book on Hatch– Chapter Four UNESCO India, undated (Box 4, Folder 70)
    - Book on Hatch–Chapter Five UNESCO Ceylon, 1953; undated (Box 4, Folder 71)
    - Book on Hatch–Chapter Six Colorado River Tribe, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 72)
    - Conference of the Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations in Quebec, 1945 (Box 4, Folder 73)
    - Stills for Give Us the Earth, undated (Box 4, Folder 74)
  - Subseries 5: Photo Albums
    - Ceylon and Around the World (1), circa 1950s (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Ceylon and Around the World (2), circa 1950s (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Ceylon and Around the World (3), circa 1950s (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Ceylon and Around the World (4), circa 1950s (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Ceylon and Around the World (5), circa 1950s (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Costa Rica Album 1 (1), circa late 1940s and 1950s (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Costa Rica Album 1 (2), circa late 1940s and 1950s (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Costa Rica Album 1 (3), circa late 1940s and 1950s (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Costa Rica Album 2 (1), circa 1940s and 1950s (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Costa Rica Album 2 (2), circa 1940s and 1950s (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Costa Rica Album 2 (3), circa 1940s and 1950s (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - 12 Costa Rica Album 3 (1), circa late 1940s and early 1950s (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - 12 Costa Rica Album 3 (2), circa late 1940s and early 1950s (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - 12 Costa Rica Album 3 (3), circa late 1940s and early 1950s (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Delhi State (1), 1950-1952 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Delhi State (2), 1950-1952 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - Delhi State (3), 1950-1952 (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - Delhi State and Ceylon (1), circa 1950s (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Delhi State and Ceylon (2), circa 1950s (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Delhi State and Ceylon (3), circa 1950s (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Mexico Album 1 (1), circa 1960s (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Mexico Album 1 (2), circa 1960s (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Mexico Album 2 (1), circa 1940s (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Mexico Album 2 (7), circa 1940s (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Mexico Album 3 (1), circa 1940s (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Mexico Album 3 (2), circa 1940s (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Mexico Album 4 (1), circa 1940s (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Mexico Album 4 (2), circa 1940s (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Mexico Album 4 (3), circa 1940s (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Mexico Album 5 (1), circa 1940s (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Mexico Album 5 (2), circa 1940s (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Mexico Album 6, circa 1940s (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Mexico Album 7 (1), circa 1940s (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Mexico Album 7 (2), circa 1940s (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - Mexico Album 7 (3), circa 1940s (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - Mexico Album 7 (4), circa 1940s (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Mexico-Agriculture (1), circa 1940s (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Mexico-Agriculture (2), circa 1940s (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Mexico-Animals, Bees, and Poultry (1), circa 1940s (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Mexico-Animals, Bees, and Poultry (2), circa 1940s (Box 7, Folder 5)
- Series V: Oversized Materials, 1947-1963; undated
  This series is arranged by format and alphabetically. It contains movie reels and access copies in DVD format of movies made by Duane Spencer. Records and two cassette tapes and access copies in CD format of talks given by Duane Spencer Hatch and the narrative portion of the movie,Up From Poverty are in this series. It also contains publicity materials, such as a movie poster from Give Us the Earth.
  - Subseries 1: Audio and Publicity Materials
    - Fundamental Education Around the World–UNESCO Radio Talk in Paris (real and access CD), 1950 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Give Us the Earth movie poster, undated (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Michigan State College Radio–Talks by Hatch about Costa Rica, India, and Mexico (real and access CD), undated (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Oversized Photo of Duane Spencer Hatch with Group for Last Visit of Prime Minister in Sri Lanka, undated (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Talk by Duane Spencer Hatch in India, undated (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Unidentified Cassette Tape-Orange (real and access CD), undated (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Unidentified Cassette Tape-Violet (real and access CD), undated (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Up From Poverty 1, undated (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Up From Poverty 2, undated (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Up From Poverty 3, undated (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Up From Poverty 4, undated (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Up From Poverty 5, undated (Box 8, Folder 12)